A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor William Smith, 1846-1848
Library of Virginia
- Executive Papers of Governor William Smith, 1846-1848., Extent: 12 boxes. (Box 1-12)
  Additional significant correspondence includes the following: Robert G. Scott re. his support of Charles Dimmock as captain of the Public Guard (1846 Jan. 14); A. Stevenson encl. a letter from Jared Sparks, Cambridge, Massachusetts, requesting permission to have a mold taken from Houdon's Statue of Washington for the purpose of having suitable casts executed from it (1846 Feb. 2); Lyman Draper, Baltimore, re. papers connected with Gen. George Rogers Clark's Illinois Campaign in the attic story of the Capitol (incl. printed circular) (1846 Feb. 23); Samuel Houston recommending Augustus Fischer as commissioner for the state of Texas (1846 Apr. 3); B.B. Minor re. his purchase of a lot & buildings on Franklin St. which runs into the public grounds and asks for permission to pull down the wall to the rear of the lot (incl. letter from Charles Dimmock & drawing) (1846 Apr. 22); I.A. Goddin proposing to take the slates off the old Museum Building, remove the woodwork, etc., for the courthouse contemplated to be erected on the Public Square (1846 May 18); Goddin re. his proposal for the erection of a courthouse (1846 May 21); William O. Yeatman proposing to serve as superintendent of the work at the Capitol & Courthouse (1846 May 23); Goddin proposing modifications to the plan for the new courthouse (1846 June 12); Goddin proposing to make panel shutters or venetian blinds for the windows to be placed in the principal story of the courthouse (1846 July 9); William N. Mills re. the act of retrocession of Alexandria (1846 Aug. 3); Duval & Purcell re. the manufacture of glass for the Capitol (1846 Aug. 28); Thomas H. Ellis proposing to improve rather than remove the gun house at the Armory (1846 Sept. 23); Samuel D. Denoon's proposal to furnish grates for the Capitol (1846 Oct. 5); John M. Seeley re. grass at the Capitol & the whitewashing of the basement story (1846 Oct. 28); William Duvall asking for the erection of a building to be used for religious & other purposes on the public ground in front of the Armory (1846 Oct. 30); James E. Heath, S.H. Parker, J. Brown, Jr., & F.M. Lawson asking for permission to purchase new carpets for their offices in the Capitol (1846 Nov. 3); S.H. Parker & F.M. Lawson requesting that the furnaces & pipes which have been provided for warming the chamber of the House of Delegates (1846 Nov. 3); William D. Pemberton, Secretary of the Virginia Literary Association, requesting donations of books & papers of a literary or historical character (1846 Nov. 13); Thomas Vannerson, Clerk of the Committee of Propositions & Grievances, requesting a new stove & pipe for the Committee Room (1846 Dec. 2); John M. Seeley re. the completion of the painting & glazing of the Capitol (1846 Dec. 17); P.H. Russell re. his work stuccoing & plastering the Capitol (1847 Jan. 7); Lyman C. Draper re. the Illinois papers, Gen. George Rogers Clark, & Daniel Boone (1847 Jan. 25); Col. John F. Hamtramck responding to the Governor's address to the volunteers (1847 Feb. 16); J.A. Early, Maj. Virginia Volunteers, Ft. Monroe, re. the delay in the embarkation of the remaining companies of Virginia Volunteers (1847 Feb. 24); G.A. Portfield, Carmago, re. the defeat of Santa Anna & the arrival of the 1st Battalion of Virginia Volunteers (1847 Mar. 7); John M. Seeley requesting an advance to enable him to finish his contract to paint the Capitol (1847 Mar. 8); H. Meigs, Secretary of the Farmer's Club, encl. a circular from the Secretary of the Royal Society of Agriculture in Paris (1847 May 7); John Latourrette asking if his map of Mississippi was received by the governor (includes a correct map of the seat of the war & adjacent country in Mexico) (1847 May 7); a "Virginian" encl. a notice protesting against a boxing match to be held in Virginia between Young Caunt & Yankee Sullivan (1847 Apr. 20); an anonymous letter from Mount Pleasant, Ohio, regarding the question of slavery in the territories (1847 June 13); Committee of the Common Hall of Richmond re. the erection of a building on Capitol Square on the southwestern corner (1847 Sept. 30); John Hamtramck encl. a letter from Capt. Smith P. Bankhead, 1st Virginia Regiment, re. recruitment problems (1848 Jan. 10); W.C. Rives, William Green, & George W. Thompson, commissioners on behalf of the state of Virginia, regarding the result of their conferences with the commissioners of Ohio for the settlement of the boundary between the states (1848 Jan. 27); J.R. Anderson, President of the Armory Iron Company, encl. letters sent to him from Charles Dimmock as Superintendent of the Armory regarding the dispute between them (1848 Feb. 1); Maj. J.A. Early, Virginia Volunteers, re. a report of his death & his leave of absence (1848 Feb. 1); W.S. Goodwyn re. the petition of Southampton Indians asking for the appointment of trustees to take charge of their property in Southampton County (1848 Feb. 15); U.S. National Medical Association advocating a system of registration of births, marriages, & deaths (1848 Mar. 1); James M. Mason, U.S. Senate, re. his appointment as visitor of the University of Virginia (includes opinion of S.S. Baxter) (1848 Mar. 3); Lt. E.S. Gay, Public Guard, requesting new quarters for himself & his family (1848 Apr. 15); C. Crozet encl. a resolution of the General Assembly that the Board of Public Works cause to be prepared by C. Crozet a lithographic map of the state of Virginia exhibiting all railroads, canals, & turnpike roads (1848 Apr. 16); E.S. Duncan resigning as judge of the 18th Judicial Circuit (1848 Apr. 18); James T. Ames re. his proposal to make three presentation swords (1848 Apr. 21); Alexandre Vattemare re. his system of cultural exchanges (1848 Apr. 26); James H. Mason, Washington, recommending George H. Lee as judge of the General court to supply the vacancy occasioned by the resignation of Judge Duncan (1848 Apr. 28); George H. Lee accepting an appointment as judge of the General Court occasioned by the resignation of E.S. Duncan (1848 May 20); James Roy Micou re. a burglary committed by one of his servants (includes "Runaway" broadside) (1848 June 7); John W. Nash accepting a commission as judge of the General Court & Circuit Superior Court of Law & Chancery for the 2nd Judicial District (1848 Sept. 2); R.H. Wood, Superintendent of Quarantine at City Point, re. cases of small pox on board the Ship Alexander (1848 Sept. 13); James A. Scott, Chairman of the Whig Vigilance Committee, requesting the Armory to fire a salute on the occasion of the election of Gen. Taylor (1848 Nov. 20); F.B. Vionis, lawyer & doctor, proposing to organize a phalanstere for the free negroes of Virginia (1848 Dec. 1); J.M. Mason encl. a letter of Elisha Whittlesey & a resolution of the Board of Managers of the Washington National Monument Office that the piece of cornerstone of the Washington National Monument be presented to the delegation of each state in Congress (1848 Dec. 4); and Joseph C. Cabell accepting an appointment as visitor of the University of Virginia (1848 Apr. 13).
  Other noteworthy items include the following: qualification of William Smith as governor of Virginia (1846 Jan. 1); proclamation of Lt. Gov. John F. Wiley for an election in the House of Representatives occasioned by the death of William Taylor (incl. letter of John W. Davis, Speaker of the House of Representatives) (1846 Jan. 24); bond of Henry Van Buren as weigh master of livestock for the city of Richmond (1846 Feb. 27); proclamation of Lt. Gov. John F. Wiley for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of James H. Piper (1846 Mar. 30); N.P. Clerk of the General Court, re. more space for the room used for the Clerk's Office & courtroom of the Superior Court of Chancery (1846 Apr. 7); proclamations by the governor & lieutenant governor offering rewards for the apprehension of escaped convicts (1846 May 5 & 9, June 17, July 29, Aug. 7 & 19, Sept. 4, Nov. 7 & 9; 1847 Jan. 1 & 23, Feb. 6, Apr. 24, June 9, July 15, Aug. 16, Sept. 2, Nov. 15, 17, & 25, Dec. 8, 14, & 18; 1848 Jan. 21, Mar. 2, 8, 9, 17, & 20, May 3 & 6, July 11, Aug. 16 & 26); proposals to superintend the repairs of the Capitol (1846 May 16); proposals for painting & glazing the courthouse to be erected in Richmond (1846 May 18); estimates & proposals of John S. Jones & others for warming the new courthouse (1846 May 18); proposal of John M. Seeley to paint all the woodwork of the Capitol (1846 May 18); proposal of John Freeman & John H. Freeman for building the woodwork & slating the roof of the new courthouse (1846 May 18); proposals for painting the Capitol & Courthouse (1846 May 18); proposals for stuccoing the exterior of the Capitol (1846 May 18); proposals & estimates for building the new courthouse on Capitol Square (1846 May 18); proposal of Beazley & Quarles to do the brickwork & slating the roof of the new courthouse (1846 May 22); proclamation of Gov. William Smith for the formation of thirty companies of volunteers to be formed into regiments when mustered into service of the United States as a result of the act of Congress declaring war on the Republic of Mexico (incl. letter of William L. Marcy, Secretary of War, and act of Congress) (1846 May 23); specifications for building a new courthouse on the site of the old Museum Building on Capitol Square (1846 May [N.D.]); recommendations for judgeship of the Court of Appeals to fill the vacancy occasioned by the death of Judge R.C. Stanard (1846 June 15); agreement between the President & Directors of the Board of Public Works & Charles F. Osborne for the lease of the water power from the James River Canal for the use of the Armory (1846 June 17); order of Governor Smith that the buildings on the western corner of Capitol Square be removed (1846 Oct. 2); proclamation of Governor Smith for an election in Lunenburg County to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the death of John T. Street (1846 Oct. 13); resolutions of the Chamber of Commerce of St. Louis for a convention to consider the powers & duties of the General Government to assist, protect, & advance the inland commerce of the country by the removal of dangerous obstructions from the Mississippi, Ohio, Missouri, & other rivers & highways of trade (1846 Oct. 13); proclamation of Governor Smith for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the death of John Guerrant (1846 Oct. 30); proclamation of Gov. Smith for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the death of David Campbell (1846 Nov. 3); proclamation of Gov. Smith calling for a regiment for immediate service during the War with Mexico (includes letter of William L. Marcy, Secretary of War, general orders of the Adjutant General's Office, & an act providing for the prosecution of the existing war between the United States & Mexico) (1846 Nov. 18); agreement, bond, & contract of Francis H. Deane as vaccine agent (1846 Nov. 18 & 1847 Oct. 1); account of John M. Seeley for painting & glazing of the Capitol (1846 Dec. 17); proceedings of the Board of Commissioners re. the appointment of field officers to the regiment of volunteers called from Virginia by the General Government (1846 Dec. 21); bond of Isaac A. Goddin for building the new courthouse (1847 Mar. 13); proceedings of the Select Committee to consider the joint resolution of the General Assembly of Ohio re. the boundary controversy between Ohio & Virginia (1847 Mar. 25); proclamation of Raleigh T. Daniel for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of William A. Spark (1847 Apr. 7); recommendation of Francis H. Pierpont to be appointed on behalf of Virginia to settle the jurisdiction between Virginia & the state of Ohio on the Ohio river (1847 Apr. 15); proclamation of Lt. Gov. R.T. Daniel for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates for Morgan County occasioned by the contested election between Andrew Michael, Jr., & William Thompson (1847 May 10); proclamation of Lt. Gov. Daniel for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of Fayette McMullen (1847 May 10); proclamation of Gov. Smith for an election to supply the vacancy in Congress occasioned by the death of George C. Dromgoole (1847 June 22); proclamation of Gov. Smith for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the death of Lewis Neal (1847 July 15); proclamation of Lt. Gov. R.T. Daniel for an election to supply the vacancy in the State Senate occasioned by the death of Carter M. Braxton (1847 July 30); proceedings of the New York Prison Association calling for a convention for the purpose of taking into consideration the criminal laws of the different states (1847 July 27); proclamation of Gov. Smith for an election to supply the vacancy in the House of Delegates occasioned by the resignation of M.B. Nowlin (1847 Nov. 13); preamble & resolution of the Ohio Legislature approving the plan of Asa Whitney for a railroad to the Pacific (1848 Feb. 18); recommendations for commissioners to superintend the presidential elections (1848 July & Aug.); recommendations for David May, Robert R. Collier, & John W. Nash to fill the vacancy occasioned by the death of Judge James H. Gholson (1848 July); inscriptions of swords voted by the General Assembly to Gen. Zachary Taylor, Lt. Col. Mathew M. Payne, & Lt. Col. John Garland for their conduct during the Mexican War (1848 Aug. 31); proclamation of Lt. Gov. John F. Wiley for an election in the House of Delegates occasioned by the resignation of John W. Nash (includes letter of resignation) (1848 Sept. 18); proclamation of Gov. Smith for an election in the State Senate occasioned by the resignation of James H. Cox (1848 Nov. 14); proclamation of Gov. Smith announcing the election of electors for President & Vice President (1848 Nov. 27); drawings of fountains for Capitol Square (1848 [N.D.]); and an estimate of the cost of the woodwork, slating, copper, gutters, tin water spouts, hinges, bolts, locks, etc., about the Courthouse to be built on the Public Square (Undated).
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1846
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - February
      - 2-14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - March
      - 2-15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - April
      - 1-13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - May
      - 1-11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 13-18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - June
      - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 11-20 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 23-29 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - August
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 17-29 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - September
      - 1-10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 11-30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - November
      - 2-14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Retrocession of Alexandria. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1847
    - January
      - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - February
      - 1-20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 21-27 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - March
      - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 21-31 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - April
      - 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 12-29 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - May
      - 1-10 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 11-31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 17-30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - August
      - 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - September
      - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - 11-30 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - October
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - 17-29 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - November
      - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 22-30 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - December
      - 2-15 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 16-31 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 1848
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - February
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 16-29 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - April
      - 1-22 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - 23-30 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - May
      - 1-7 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 8-18 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 19-30 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - June
      - 1-14 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - 16-29 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - 17-31 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - August
      - 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - 16-31 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - September
      - 2-15 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - October (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - November
      - 1-20 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - 21-30 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - 16-31 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Pardons
      - Hill, Hunter (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Johnston, John J. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Oversized (Clamshell Box)
  - 1846
    - Feb. 28 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Mar. 11 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - June 15 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Oct. 30 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Nov. 14 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1847
    - Jan. 13 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Feb. 6 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - May 27 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - June 25 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - July 12 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Sept. [N.D.] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 1848
    - Jan. 27 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Feb. 17 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Feb. 23 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - July 25 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - July 29 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Nov. 1 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Nov. 11 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Nov. 14 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Nov. 20 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Dec. 4 (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Oversized (Newspaper Box)
  - 1846
    - Jan. 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Jan. 14 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - May 18 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - May 18 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - June 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - June 15 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Oct. 1 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Nov. 17 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Nov. 22 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 1847
    - Mar. 30 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - May 31 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - June 25 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - July 29 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - July 30 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Sept. 10 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Nov. 13 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - 1848
    - Oct. 31 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Dec. 27 (Box 12, Folder 18)